<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xmlTree.xsl"?>
<Root>
  <Tree treeText="Ukraine. Radioactive contamination" treeDescription="Edition 2011 р.">
    <branch id="b00">
      <branchText>Introduction</branchText>
      <branchDescription></branchDescription>
      <link>Documents/part0_eng.htm</link>
      <indexedWords>Atlas presents the consequences of the accident at Chornobyl nuclear power plant occurred on April 26, 1986.

Apart from radioactive contamination of the territory of Ukraine, a lot of attention is paid to principal problems of suffered people and society after the accident.

The Atlas consists of 4 sections:

First section contains the maps of the field of contamination by cesium-137, strontium-90, sum of plutonium isotopes and predictive map of contamination by americium-241. For the territory of Ukraine in general these maps are presented on scale 1:2 500 000 and for the most contaminated territory (exclusion zone) on scale 1:300,000. Maps of contamination of Ukraine by cesium-137 and strontium-90 before the accident are presented for comparison (scale 1:12 000 000). Additionally this section contains scheme-map of radioactive waste repositories in the exclusion zone and maps of contamination by cesium-137 of the cities of Korosten and Slavutych and adjacent territories. Latter maps have been plotted using the results of aerial gamma survey on scale 1:25 000, however in the Atlas these maps are presented on scale 1:100 000.

Second section of the Atlas comprises the maps presenting the impact of radioactive contamination on human being and medical consequences of the accident. The most important maps of the section – total effective doses of internal and external irradiation for 20 and 70 years after the accident (scale 1:2 500 000) and exposure doses of thyroid gland for seven age categories of population (scale 1:5 000 000). These maps have been prepared using the data of the Research Centre for Radiation Medicine of Academy of Medical Sciences of Ukraine and Radiation Protection Institute ATS Ukraine. The map of milk contamination by cesium-137 (average annual values for the most contaminated regions, 1991-2006) and other maps are included in the section.

Third section contains the maps of social and economic consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe - for zones of radioactive contamination according to the legislation in force, number and composition of population having the status of affected as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe, improving children's health of this category, etc. Maps reflecting migration of population from contaminated territories and housing construction in the framework of the Program on liquidation of Chornobyl catastrophe consequences are also included in this section. Maps of this section are presented on scales 1:2 500 000 and 1:5 000 000.

The fourth section includes reference materials and maps. In particular, map of stations for radiometric monitoring network of the State Hydrometeorological Service of Ukraine, maps of soils, maps of forest zoning by the density of radioactive contamination by cesium-137 are presented.

All Atlas’s sections contain explanatory texts explaining peculiarities of phenomena presented on the maps and its interpretation.

Atlas is oriented on the employees of executive authorities of all levels, scientists and wide circle of readers.</indexedWords>
      <Frame>contents</Frame>
      <ImageIndex>1</ImageIndex>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Editorial Board</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Documents/autors_eng.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Chairman of editorial board:
          ##KHOLOSHA V.I.


          Members of editorial board:

          ##Baryakhtar V.G. – Deputy Chairman, Doctor of Geography, Academician of NAS of Ukraine

          ##Tabachnyi L.Ya. - Deputy Chairman
          ##Lytvynenko O.Ye. – responsible secretary, Candidate of Technical Science
          ##Bondar A.L., Candidate of Technical Science
          ##Kashparov V.O., Doctor of Physics and Mathematics
          ##Likhtarev I.A., Doctor of Physics and Mathematics
          ##Rudenko L.G., Doctor of Geography, Academician of NAS of Ukraine
          ##Chabanyuk V.S., Candidate of Physics and Mathematics
          ##Shestopalov V.M. – Doctor of Geology, Academician of NAS of Ukraine


          Group of authors:
          ##Tabachnyi L.Ya. – (Scientific supervisor)
          ##Davydchuk S.V. (Deputy scientific supervisor)
          ##Lytvynenko O.Ye. – (Deputy scientific supervisor), Candidate of Technical Science
          ##Gaidar O.V., Candidate of Physics and Mathematics
          ##Kovgan L.M., Doctor of Biology
          ##Likhtarev I.A., Doctor of Physics and Mathematics
          ##Lynnyk S.O.
          ##Lyovshyn Ye.B., Candidate of Physics and Mathematics
          ##Reshetnyk V.I.
          ##Savchuk O.R.
          ##Samorodov Ye.L.
          ##Sotnikov S.O.
          ##Sotnikova G.Ye.


          Authors of dosimetric and thyreodosimetric data:
          ##Likhtarev I.A., (Scientific supervisor), Doctor of Physics and Mathematics
          ##Berkovsky V.V., Doctor of Biology
          ##Kovgan L.M., Doctor of Biology
          ##Kairo I.A.
          ##Shpak V.M.


          Translated by:
          ##Bobriakov S.V.


          Authors express sincere gratitude to Bugay D.M., Voitsekhovich O.V., Golubchikov M.V., Grytsenko M.M., Kashparov V.O., Lev T.D., Proskura M.I., Prister B.S., Skalsky O.O., Tkachenko N.V., Shpyga P.S. for possibility to use prepared by them data.


          Authors will keep special gratitude to those who already died: Lyovshyn Ye.B. – coauthor of maps included in section I, and Babich O.A and Skudnova L.V. who prepared the materials used during drafting the first and partially the second and third editions of present Atlas.


          Radiometry survey materials have been used while mapping the radioactive contamination maps. These surveys have been executed by Ukrainian Academy of Agrarian Sciences, Academy of Medical Sciences, National Academy of Sciences, Ministry of Health of Ukraine, Ministry of Agrarian Policy of Ukraine, geological and meteorological services, other organizations and institutions participated in large-scale survey of contaminated territories. Also the data of aerial gamma-spectrometry of aerial geophysics division of geological service of Ukraine have been used. This activity aimed at assessment of radioactive contamination levels on the territory of Ukraine as a result of the accident at Chornobyl NPP has been executed in the framework of national programs.

          Materials of the Center of Medical Statistics of the Ministry of Health of Ukraine have been used while mapping the maps of medical consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe.

          Materials of the Ministry of Emergencies of Ukraine and State Statistics Committee of Ukraine have been used while mapping of social and economical consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe.
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>contents</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Prephase</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Documents/part0_1_eng.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          More than 25 years elapsed after the date of the accident at Chornobyl NPP on April 26, 1986. Since then significant changes took place in the society, social-political and economical way of life in Ukraine. However consequences of this accident are still topical and require a consolidated participation of whole country in resolution of the problems caused by these consequences.

          Millions of Ukrainian citizens have been affected as a result the accident at Chornobyl NPP – the largest technogeneous catastrophe in nuclear power industry. Impact of the accident on public health, its social and economic consequences determine living conditions in the contaminated territories today and will continue to do so for dozens of coming years.

          Beginning from the first days of liquidation of the accident considerable efforts have been focused on studying the levels of radioactive contamination of environment. Radiation monitoring system has been established which includes hundreds of laboratories and radiological monitoring posts. Until now this infrastructure executes regular assessment of actual radiation status of contaminated territories and controls contamination of products produced here. Hundreds of thousands of measurements were exercised to determine radionuclides’ content in water, atmospheric aerosols, fallouts and sediments, soil, agricultural and forestry products. Whole territory of Ukraine has been surveyed with different levels of details using aerial gamma-spectrometric methods. Annual dosimetric passportization is executed in the settlements enrolled in the zones of enhanced radioecological monitoring and guaranteed voluntary relocation and in the villages of compulsory relocation zone where local people still live. Its results are the basis for planning and execution of counter-radiation measures and for preparation of proposals regarding reviewing the boundaries of radioactive contamination zones.

          Maps of radioactive contamination of the territory of Ukraine have been mapped on the basis of results of monitoring surveys. These maps have been published in a number of publications, in particular - special atlases of contamination of Europe by cesium [6], radioactive contamination of the European part of Russia, Belarus and Ukraine [7], atlas of Chornobyl exclusion zone [8]. Main attention in the publications is paid to contamination of the territory by cesium-137 which is a basic dose-forming radionuclide during the late phase of Chornobyl accident. Maps of contamination of the territory by other radionuclides having a great radiological importance - strontium-90, plutonium isotopes, americium-241 - for the territory of Ukraine are just illustrative.

          Since the publication of mentioned editions significant activities have been executed aimed at analysis and sorting of radiological monitoring data. Part of the territory has been surveyed additionally mainly by aerial gamma-spectrometric survey and to a lesser degree by surface sample-taking. New results of studies allowed to prepare more precise maps of contamination of Ukraine by cesium-137 and and based on them to develop the maps of contamination by strontium-90, plutonium isotopes, and americium-241. Therefore it became necessary to publish new maps of contamination of Ukraine by cesium-137 and maps of contamination by other radionuclides which were previously printed only as small-scale charts.

          However separate maps of radioactive contamination do not provide complete picture of its impact on the health of population, creation of comprehensive edition became necessary.

          Ionizing radiation is a major determinative factor in the scope of radiation accident. Irradiation dose received by human being as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe and that will be received in future on condition of living on the contaminated territory is an integral index reflecting the impact of all radionuclides. It is also important that during last ten years (and in coming years as well) the major contribution in total radiation dose has been made by internal irradiation due to intake of food products produced on the territory of radioactive contamination zones, mainly in northern regions of Ukrainian Polissya. Map of milk contamination mapped by the results of long-term observations on contaminated territories is included in the Atlas.

          Complex of problems caused by Chornobyl catastrophe requires considerable intellectual, administrative, social and public and economic efforts aimed at its resolution. Accident consequences liquidation in the framework of national-wide program of overcoming the consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe have been financed for some time at the account of national Chornobyl fund formed from a special charge (tax). Now it is financed mainly from general fund of State budget of Ukraine.

          Third section of the Atlas presents the problems of social and economic consequences of the catastrophe. It contains inter alia two principally important maps – the map of the radioactive contamination zones according to Ukrainian legislation in force and the map of one of the possible composition of contamination zones according to dosimetric passportization executed during the last years.

          Special reference section has been included in the Atlas due to complexity and multi-dimensional nature of the problems related to Chornobyl catastrophe consequences. This section contains the maps of soils of Ukraine since different types of soils determine the various radionuclides transition coefficients from soil to vegetable food that later on get in the human body via food chains. Presence of soils with high transition coefficient is determinative in forming of internal irradiation dose of inhabitants of Ukrainian Polissya. This section contains the maps of radiation monitoring network and zoning of forests by the density of radioactive contamination by cesium-137. Methods used for development of basic maps of the Atlas are briefly described.
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>contents</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Content</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Documents/sitemap_eng.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>фыва тест фыва</indexedWords>
        <Frame>contents</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Terms and abbreviations</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Documents/terms_eng.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          More than 25 years elapsed after the date of the accident at Chornobyl NPP on April 26, 1986. Since then significant changes took place in the society, social-political and economical way of life in Ukraine. However consequences of this accident are still topical and require a consolidated participation of whole country in resolution of the problems caused by these consequences.

          Millions of Ukrainian citizens have been affected as a result the accident at Chornobyl NPP – the largest technogeneous catastrophe in nuclear power industry. Impact of the accident on public health, its social and economic consequences determine living conditions in the contaminated territories today and will continue to do so for dozens of coming years.

          Beginning from the first days of liquidation of the accident considerable efforts have been focused on studying the levels of radioactive contamination of environment. Radiation monitoring system has been established which includes hundreds of laboratories and radiological monitoring posts. Until now this infrastructure executes regular assessment of actual radiation status of contaminated territories and controls contamination of products produced here. Hundreds of thousands of measurements were exercised to determine radionuclides’ content in water, atmospheric aerosols, fallouts and sediments, soil, agricultural and forestry products. Whole territory of Ukraine has been surveyed with different levels of details using aerial gamma-spectrometric methods. Annual dosimetric passportization is executed in the settlements enrolled in the zones of enhanced radioecological monitoring and guaranteed voluntary relocation and in the villages of compulsory relocation zone where local people still live. Its results are the basis for planning and execution of counter-radiation measures and for preparation of proposals regarding reviewing the boundaries of radioactive contamination zones.

          Maps of radioactive contamination of the territory of Ukraine have been mapped on the basis of results of monitoring surveys. These maps have been published in a number of publications, in particular - special atlases of contamination of Europe by cesium [6], radioactive contamination of the European part of Russia, Belarus and Ukraine [7], atlas of Chornobyl exclusion zone [8]. Main attention in the publications is paid to contamination of the territory by cesium-137 which is a basic dose-forming radionuclide during the late phase of Chornobyl accident. Maps of contamination of the territory by other radionuclides having a great radiological importance - strontium-90, plutonium isotopes, americium-241 - for the territory of Ukraine are just illustrative.

          Since the publication of mentioned editions significant activities have been executed aimed at analysis and sorting of radiological monitoring data. Part of the territory has been surveyed additionally mainly by aerial gamma-spectrometric survey and to a lesser degree by surface sample-taking. New results of studies allowed to prepare more precise maps of contamination of Ukraine by cesium-137 and and based on them to develop the maps of contamination by strontium-90, plutonium isotopes, and americium-241. Therefore it became necessary to publish new maps of contamination of Ukraine by cesium-137 and maps of contamination by other radionuclides which were previously printed only as small-scale charts.

          However separate maps of radioactive contamination do not provide complete picture of its impact on the health of population, creation of comprehensive edition became necessary.

          Ionizing radiation is a major determinative factor in the scope of radiation accident. Irradiation dose received by human being as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe and that will be received in future on condition of living on the contaminated territory is an integral index reflecting the impact of all radionuclides. It is also important that during last ten years (and in coming years as well) the major contribution in total radiation dose has been made by internal irradiation due to intake of food products produced on the territory of radioactive contamination zones, mainly in northern regions of Ukrainian Polissya. Map of milk contamination mapped by the results of long-term observations on contaminated territories is included in the Atlas.

          Complex of problems caused by Chornobyl catastrophe requires considerable intellectual, administrative, social and public and economic efforts aimed at its resolution. Accident consequences liquidation in the framework of national-wide program of overcoming the consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe have been financed for some time at the account of national Chornobyl fund formed from a special charge (tax). Now it is financed mainly from general fund of State budget of Ukraine.

          Third section of the Atlas presents the problems of social and economic consequences of the catastrophe. It contains inter alia two principally important maps – the map of the radioactive contamination zones according to Ukrainian legislation in force and the map of one of the possible composition of contamination zones according to dosimetric passportization executed during the last years.

          Special reference section has been included in the Atlas due to complexity and multi-dimensional nature of the problems related to Chornobyl catastrophe consequences. This section contains the maps of soils of Ukraine since different types of soils determine the various radionuclides transition coefficients from soil to vegetable food that later on get in the human body via food chains. Presence of soils with high transition coefficient is determinative in forming of internal irradiation dose of inhabitants of Ukrainian Polissya. This section contains the maps of radiation monitoring network and zoning of forests by the density of radioactive contamination by cesium-137. Methods used for development of basic maps of the Atlas are briefly described.
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>contents</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Literature</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Documents/references_eng.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          1.Methodological guide: Reconstruction and prediction of exposure doses of population living on the territory of Ukraine impacted by radioactive contamination as a result of accident at Chornobyl NPP. Methodology-97 (in Russian) / Ministry of Health of Ukraine, Academy of Medical Sciences of Ukraine, Ministry of Ukraine of Emergencies and Affairs of Population Protection from the Consequences of Chornobyl Catastrophe, Scientific Center of Radiation Medicine of the Academy of Medical Sciences of Ukraine, Radiation Protection Institute of the Academy of Technical Sciences of Ukraine – Kyiv, 1998. – 76 p.
          2.Methodological guide: Radiation and dosimetric passportization of settlements on the territory of Ukraine radioactively contaminated as a result of the accident at Chornobyl NPP including dosimetric passportization of thyroid: Methodology-96 (In Ukrainian) / Ministry of Health of Ukraine, Academy of Medical Sciences of Ukraine, Ministry of Ukraine of Emergency Affairs and Population Protection from Consequences of Chornobyl Catastrophe, Scientific Center of Radiation Medicine of the Academy of Medical Sciences of Ukraine, Radiation Protection Institute of the Academy of Technical Sciences of Ukraine. - Kyiv, 1996.
          3.Norms of radiation safety of Ukraine: NRSU-97 (in Ukrainian) / National hygienic regulations. - Kyiv, 1997.
          4.Norms of radiation safety of Ukraine: Addendum: Radiation protection from sources of potential irradiation: NRSU-97/D-2000 (in Ukrainian) / National hygienic regulations. - Kyiv, 2000.
          5.Encyclopedia of Physics / Edited by A. M. Prokhorov — M., 1994. 704 p.
          6.Atlas of caesium deposition on Europe after the Chernobyl accident. – Luxembourg: Luxembourg Office for Official Publications of the European Communities, 1998.
          7.Atlas of radioactive contamination of European part of Russia, Belarus and Ukraine (in Russian). - Moscow: Federal Service for Geodesy and Cartography of Russia, 1998. - 143 p.
          8.Atlas of Chornobyl exclusion zone (in Ukrainian). - Kyiv: Scientific and production association "Kartograpfhiya", 1996. - 26 p.
          9.Methodological guide: Radiation and dosimetric passportization of settlements on the territory of Ukraine radioactively contaminated as a result of the accident at Chornobyl NPP including dosimetric passportization of thyroid: Methodology-96/ Ministry of Health of Ukraine, Academy of Medical Sciences of Ukraine, Ministry of Ukraine of Emergency Affairs and Population Protection from Consequences of Chornobyl Catastrophe, Scientific Center of Radiation Medicine of the Academy of Medical Sciences of Ukraine, Radiation Protection Institute of the Academy of Technical Sciences of Ukraine. - Kyiv, 1996.
          10.Law of Ukraine of February 27, 1991 №791а - ХІІ. On legal regime of radioactively contaminated territory as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe.
          11.Methodological guide: Reconstruction and prediction of exposure doses of population living on the territory of Ukraine impacted by radioactive contamination as a result of accident at Chornobyl NPP. Methodology-97/ Ministry of Health of Ukraine, Academy of Medical Sciences of Ukraine, Ministry of Ukraine of Emergencies and Affairs of Population Protection from the Consequences of Chornobyl Catastrophe, Scientific Center of Radiation Medicine of the Academy of Medical Sciences of Ukraine, Radiation Protection Institute of the Academy of Technical Sciences of Ukraine – Kyiv, 1998. – 76 p.
          12.Likhtarev, I. and Kovgan, L. “General structure of Chornobyl exposure sources and doses of Ukrainian population. - ”International Journal of Radiation Medicine, 1999, 1 (1). - р. 29-38.
          13.Health status of suffered population of Ukraine and resources of health protection 15 years after Chornobyl catastrophe: Statistical and analytical reference book in two parts. - K.: Ministry of Health of Ukraine, Ministry of Ukraine of Emergencies and Affairs of Population Protection from the Consequences of Chornobyl Catastrophe, Center of Medical Statistics of the Ministry of Health of Ukraine, 2001. 1st part - 188 p., 2nd part - 309 p.
          14.Law of Ukraine of February 28, 1991 №796 - ХІІ. On Status and Social Protection of Population Suffered from Chornobyl Catastrophe.
          15.Provisions on organization and functioning of State register of people suffered as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe / approved by Decree of the Cabinet of Ministers of Ukraine №571 of June 9, 1997.
          16.Chornobyl catastrophe / edited by V.G. Baryakhtar. - Kyiv: Editorial House of Annual Issue “Export of Ukraine”, 1997. - 576 p.
          17.Fifteen years of Chornobyl catastrophe. Overcoming experience: National report of Ukraine / edited by V.V. Durdynets – Kyiv: Ministry of Emergencies, 2001. – 144 p.
          18.Health status of suffered population of Ukraine 20 years after Chornobyl catastrophe: Statistical and analytical reference book in two parts. - K.: Ministry of Health of Ukraine, Ministry of Ukraine of Emergencies and Affairs of Population Protection from the Consequences of Chornobyl Catastrophe, Center of Medical Statistics of the Ministry of Health of Ukraine, 2007. 1st part - 177 p., 2nd part - 254 p.
          19.20 years of Chornobyl catastrophe. Look to future. National report of Ukraine / edited by V.I. Baloga – K.: Ministry of Emergencies, 2006. – 224 p.
          20.Law of Ukraine of February 28, 1991 №796 - ХІІ. On Status and Social Protection of Population Suffered from Chornobyl Catastrophe.
          21.Law of Ukraine of February 27, 1991 №791а - ХІІ. On legal regime of radioactively contaminated territory as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe.
          22.Decree of the Council of Ministers of Ukrainian SSR of July 23, 1991 №106 On the organization of execution of the decrees of Verkhovna Rada of Ukrainian SSR on the order of putting in force of the laws of Ukrainian SSR “On legal status of the territory radioactively contaminated as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe” and "On Status and Social Protection of Population Suffered from Chornobyl Catastrophe”.
          23.Execution of the program on liquidation of the consequences of the accident at Chornobyl NPP in 1st half of 2007. - Kyiv: Data-computing center of State Statistics Committee of Ukraine, 2007. – 48 p.
          24.On the status of overcoming the consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe in Ukraine in 2006-2007 / Annual report of Ukraine (in Ukrainian) / edited by Kholosha V.I. – Kyiv 2008. – 112 p.
          25.Law of Ukraine “On the State Budget of Ukraine for 2011” of 23.12.2010, №2857-VI.
          26.Chornobyl: Post accident program of construction / edited by G.K. Zlobin and V.Ya. Pinchuk. – Kyiv: Publishing house "Ivan Fedorov" with participation the Academy of Construction of Ukraine, MES, NVP "Rosa", 1998. - 440 p.
          27.Order of the Cabinet of Ministers of Ukraine of 12.01.1993, №17-r.
          28.Order of the Cabinet of Ministers of Ukraine of 27.01.1995, №37-r.
          29.Law of Ukraine “On attribution of certain settlements of Volyn and Rivne regions to zones of guaranteed voluntary relocation” (Bulletin of Verkhovna Rada, 2004, №12, p. 161).
          30.Atlas of caesium deposition on Europe after the Chernobyl accident. – Luxembourg: Luxembourg Office for Official Publications of the European Communities, 1998.
          31.Recommendations on forest management on condition of radioactive contamination/ Edited by V.P. Krasnov – K., 2008. - 82 p.
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>contents</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
    </branch>

    <branch id="b01">
      <branchText>Section I. Radioactive contamination of the territory of Ukraine</branchText>
      <branchDescription></branchDescription>
      <link></link>
      <indexedWords></indexedWords>
      <Frame>contents</Frame>
      <ImageIndex>0</ImageIndex>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Radioactive contamination of the territory of Ukraine</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Documents/part1_eng.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Radioactive contamination of the territory of Ukraine

          Field of natural radioactivity of the Earth exists since the moment of creation of our planet. It is formed both by radionuclides appeared as a result of nuclear transformations during creation of solar system and did not decay for almost five billions years of existence of the Earth and by cosmic radiation. More than 60 natural radionuclides are observed in the biosphere of the Earth. The main radionuclides contributing into the human body burden are those related to uranium-radium and thorium series and potassium-40. Average content of uranium, thorium and potassium in the Earth crust equals 2.5*10--4%, 13.0*10-4% and 2.5% respectively. Each gram of potassium contains 119 micrograms of radioactive potassium-40. Variations in the content of these radionuclides in the surface layer of the Earth mainly depend on the types of geological material, depth of occurrence, soil formation processes and may significantly deviate from average values. Spatial distribution of uranium, characteristics of soils and climate having impact on the processes of gas exchange between soil and atmosphere determine the natural radioactivity of atmosphere. Mainly it is determined by radon-222 and its decay products. Radon-222 is an inert gas with half-life period 3.8 days and it is formed as a result of decay of radium-226. To the south of 55° of northern latitude concentration values of radon-222 in the air varies predominantly between 3.5-7.4 Bq/m3.

          Cosmic radiation of galactic and solar origin consists mainly of high-energy protons. Earth's magnetic field and its atmosphere ensure reliable protection of human being and all living things from direct impact of these destructive fluxes. Secondary cosmic radiation in the field of which the inhabitants of the Earth live is formed as a result of interaction of primary cosmic fluxes with Earth’s atmosphere, in particular of respective nuclear reactions resulting in formation of radionuclides, mainly of tritium (hydrogen-3), berilium-7, carbon-14.

          Anthropogenic sources of ionizing radiation appeared together with the natural ones since the beginning of utilization of nuclear energy. Significant global changes in radionuclide content of biosphere started from the middle of XX century due to extensive atmospheric tests of nuclear weapon carried out by nuclear states in 1950-1960s. During powerful nuclear explosions either on the earth or in the atmosphere the main part of radioactive fission products passed to stratosphere, more or less uniformly distributed there, stayed there for months and years and gradually fell on the surface of Earth. Since then short-lived radionuclides decayed and due to fallout of long-lived radionuclides – cesium-137, strontium-90, transuranium elements – global low background radioactive pollution of earth’s surface and aqueous medium have been formed. Maximal levels of soil contamination stipulated by global fallout are inherent to the region of Earth surface located between 40° and 60° of northern latitude. There is a close correlation between levels of global radioactive contamination and amounts of average annual atmospheric precipitation and it explaines somehow a non-uniform distribution of global pollution density.

          Signing by nuclear states (except France and China) of Moscow Treaty Banning Nuclear Weapons Tests in the Atmosphere, in Outer Space, and Under Water put the end to accumulation of global discharges of long-lived radionuclides.

          Underground tests of nuclear weapon and normal operation of nuclear and conventional power plants and nuclear fuel cycle facilities do not have significant impact on natural environment. Generally its additional contribution to anthropogenic background radiation has local character.

          Radio-ecological status of the territory of Ukraine before the accident

          Atlas contains the maps of global pollution of the territory of Ukraine by cesium-137 and strontium-90. While drafting the maps of contamination by cesium-137 and strontium-90 before the accident the data of regional radiological service of the Ministry of Agrarian Policy have been used [1]. Monitoring of pollution levels have been carried out at experimental grounds established in Ukraine in 1970s. In each of impacted regions there were from one to five of these grounds on the average. Average data regarding cesium-137 and strontium-90 for 1981-1985 have been used for preparation of pollution maps. Survey contamination maps of the territory of Ukraine by cesium-137 and strontium-90 before the accident - Map: Contamination of the territory of Ukraine by cesium-137 (as of July 1, 1985), Map: Contamination of the territory of Ukraine by strontium-90 (as of July 1, 1985).

          It should me mentioned that before the accident the territory of Ukraine has been quite uniformly contaminated by cesium-137 and strontium-90 of global origin. Insignificant exceeding of contamination levels in mountain area of Crimea and Carpathians can be explained by higher annual precipitation in these regions.

          Contamination caused by Chornobyl catastrophe

          For almost 40-years history of nuclear power industry there were several significant accidents at nuclear fuel cycle facilities and at nuclear reactors that caused off-site radioactive contamination. The best known of them are: at processing plant in Windscale (Great Britain) and at Kyshtym nuclear facility (USSR) in 1957, at Three Mile Island (USA) in 1979. During Three Mile Island accident 53% of fuel elements have been destroyed and almost 70% of nuclear reaction decay products moved to coolant. Meanwhile due to construction of protection facilities of reactor only insignificant part of radioactive substances has been discharged to environment [2, 3].

          Fourth power unit of Chornobyl Nuclear Power Plant pertaining to second generation of nuclear power plants with reactors of RBMK type has been commissioned in December of 1983.

          Chronology and causes of the accident at fourth power unit are described in special literature [4]. Explosion of reactor at 1:24 on the 26th of April of 1986 caused radioactive discharge of the reactor core fragments and steam-gas cloud saturated by the fuel debris of different dispersion, aerosol particles and radioactive gases.

          Wide spectrum of forms and content of discharged radioactive products, change of efficient height of discharges, duration of discharges and their non-monotonic nature, change of meteorological conditions during the most intense emission caused formation of complex fields of radioactive contamination by radionuclides and detailed investigations of their structure are still an actual task. Structure of contamination fields of Chornobyl origin is non-uniform, spotted and oblong along the air fluxes lines. Among field structures the following structures are conditionally distinguished: Macrostructure determining the main tracks and spots; mesostructure reflecting field deviations in the framework of distinguished macrostructure peculiarities; local structures (coastline anomalies, waysides, drains etc.). Field macrostructure is determined first of all by meteorological factors – direction and speed of air-mass transport. Status of atmospheric boundary layer, presence of precipitation, landscape factors stipulate mesoscale structure – mosaic of the spots with high and low contamination levels.

          There are three traces on the territory of Ukraine – western, north-eastern and southern – forming the macrostructure of the field. At the time of accident on the 26th of April, 1986 air masses near Chornobyl NPP were under the impact of the outer part of anticyclone. Within this area there were no significant changes of pressure between adjacent air masses. These conditions caused variable directions and low speed of winds. The latter did not exceed 2-3 m/sec at the air layer below 600 m. Mainly air-masses were transported to the west. On the 27th of April the pressure decreased and downpours were observed from time to time. Trajectory of the transport of discharge that occurred the day before continued to the west and north-west. Near Chornobyl NPP at 600 m height the direction of wind has been changed to the north with the speed 1-4 m/sec. Decreasing of pressure continued on 28th of April. At 100-700 m height the wind speed did not change. Wind direction changed from west to north-east due to low speed. Near-earth pressure decreasing has been continued also on the 29th of April. Wind speed in eastern direction in the near-earth layer increased to 6-16 m/sec. Wind direction on the 30th of April changed from north-east to south-west, and its speed slightly decreased. On the 1st of May wind speed increased to 10 m/sec in southern direction. On the 3rd of May there were still the winds in southern direction with registered storm winds up to 15-22 m/sec. Decreasing of wind speed to 6 m/sec in southern and south-western directions occurred on the 5th of May [4, 5]. General dynamics of discharge during this time span is presented on the fig. 1.1.



          Figure 1.1 – Dynamics on daily discharge of radioactive material to atmosphere (with ± 50% deviation) [2, 6, 7]

          Isotope content in the reactor core at the time of accident and assessments of total discharge by separate radionuclides are presented in the table 1.1.

          В табл. 1.1 наведено ізотопний склад в активній зоні реактора на момент аварії та оцінки сумарного викиду окремих радіонуклідів.

          Table 1.1 – Radionuclides accumulated in the reactor core by the time of accident and some estimations of total discharge of the most significant radionuclides during the accident at ChNPP [13]




          Group of elements


          Radionuclide


          Half-life


          Activity accumulated
          in reactor at the time of accident,
          PBq (MCi)


          Assessment of total discharged
          activity during the accident
          (PBq)


          Assessment of activity
          as of 26.04.2006
          PBq







          [6, 8]


          [9]


          [10, 11]

          [15]



          Inert gases

          Xe-133

          5.3 d

          6500 (180)

          6500

          6500

          0.000



          Volatile elements

          I-131

          8.04 d

          3200 (87)

          ~ 1800

          1200-1700

          0.000


          Te-132

          3.26 d

          2700 (73)

          ~ 1200

          1000

          0.000


          Cs-134

          2.06 y

          180 (4.9)

          ~ 54

          44-48

          0.065


          Cs-137

          30.1 y

          280 (7.6)

          ~ 85

          74-85

          46 - 53



          Intermediate elements

          Sr-89

          50.6 d

          2300 (62)

          ~ 120

          81

          0.000


          Sr-90

          28.5 y

          200 (5.4)

          ~ 10

          8

          5


          Ru-103

          39.4 d

          4800 (130)

          > 170

          170

          0.000


          Ru-106

          367 d

          2100 (57)

          > 73

          30

          0.000


          Ba-140

          12.8 d

          4800 (130)

          ~ 240

          170

          0.000



          Refractory elements*

          Zr-95

          64.0 d

          5600 (150)

          200

          170

          0.000


          Mo-99

          2.75 d

          4800 (130)

          > 170

          210

          0.000


          Ce-141

          32.5 d

          5600 (150)

          196

          200

          0.000


          Ce-144

          284 d

          3300 (89)

          ~ 120

          140

          0.000


          Pu-238

          86.4 y

          1 (0.027)

          0.035

          0.03

          0.03


          Pu-239

          24100 y

          0.85 (0.032)

          0.03

          0.03

          0.03


          Pu-240

          6553 y

          1.2 (0.023)

          0.042

          0.044

          0.042


          Pu-241

          14.7 y

          170 (4.6)

          ~ 6

          5.9

          2.29


          Cm-242

          162.8 d

          26 (0.70)

          ~ 0.9

          0.93

          0.41



          * Recently, there were estimations reduced amount of plutonium isotopes in the discharge by half [16, 17]

          Differences in the contamination structure of certain territories by different radionuclides are determined by physicochemical properties of radioactive elements. Volatile elements (iodine-131, tellurium-132, cesium-134, -137) mainly passed from reactor as highly dispersed particles and aerosols and its formation had a condensation nature. Significant extent of contamination traces and presence of spots at long distances from reactor is typical for volatile elements. Released refractory elements (zirconium-95, molybdenum-99, cerium-141,-144, plutonium-238,-239,-240,-241, curium-242) passed from reactor in relatively big fuel particles, and its fallout occurred in the exclusion zone, on the territories adjacent to ChNPP.

          Contamination by strontium isotopes has mixed nature and is mainly stipulated by fuel component of the discharge, but for the regions at the distances 150-300 km from ChNPP in the direction of southern trace, contribution of condensation components becames dominant, therefore contamination by strontium-90 has significantly spread beyond the exclusion zone. The highest levels of contamination by strontium-90 are observed along western (fuel) and within southern traces. In the latter case the particles in fallouts along the trace had both fuel and condensation origin.

          During the active phase of discharges the nature of processes in the destroyed reactor has been changed and these changes determined the discharge height and intensity. Intensive “explosive” discharge on the 26th of April that has been spread within the near-earth layer formed the narrow “explosive” western trace. Radioactive inert gases (xenon-133 and other), volatile radionuclides (iodine-131, tellurium-132, cesium-134, -137) formed radioactive clouds at significant heights (up to several kilometers) and started its movement in western and north-western directions. Gradually the discharge output decreased to certain extent due to decreasing of temperature in reactor. But since the midday of the 27th of April reactor graphite started to burn more intensively causing new discharges, especially cesium-137. During this time span contamination of the territories both in western and south-western and northern and north-eastern directions has been formed (considering the changes of wind direction at different heights). At that time started the process of filling up of destroyed reactor. On 28-30th of April intensity and height of discharges significantly decreased. This stipulated relatively insignificant contamination levels in eastern and south-eastern directions. From the 2nd to 6th of May reheating of reactor occurred causing the increasing of discharge intensity practically up to the values of the first days of the accident. Formation of southern trace occurred during this time span. Due to increasing of fuel temperature the radionuclide content of discharges has been changed. Content of refractory elements has been increased as compared with more volatile cesium. After the 6th of May radionuclide’s discharges significantly decreased and later on stopped.

          Atlas contains the maps of actual status of contamination of Ukraine by cesium-137 Map: Contamination of the territory of Ukraine by cesium-137 (as of May 10, 1986), Map: Contamination of the territory of Ukraine by cesium-137 (as of May 10, 2011), strontium-90 Map: Contamination of the territory of Ukraine by strontium-90 (as of May 10, 1986), Map: Contamination of the territory of Ukraine by strontium-90 (as of May 10, 2011), plutonium isotopes -238, -239, -240 Map: Contamination of the territory of Ukraine by plutonium isotopes and forecast of contamination by americium-241 in 2056 Map: Prediction of contamination of the territory of Ukraine by americium-241 for 2056 when concentration of americium-241 on the earth surface reaches the maximal value due to decay of plutonium-241. Since the main inventory of Chornobyl fallout activity is concentrated in the exclusion zone of Chornobyl NPP Atlas contains the maps of contamination of exclusion zone and adjacent territories Map: Contamination of the exclusion zone by cesium-137 (as of May 10, 1986), Map: Contamination of the exclusion zone by cesium-137 (as of May 10, 2011),Map: Contamination of the exclusion zone by strontium-90 (as of May 10, 1986), Map: Contamination of the exclusion zone by strontium-90 (as of May 10, 2011), Map: Contamination of the exclusion zone by plutonium isotopes, Map: Contamination of the exclusion zone by americium-241, Map: Prediction of contamination of the exclusion zone by americium-241 for 2056. Also the map-scheme of radwaste repositories in the close zone of ChNPP is presented. This map shows locations of temporary localization of radioactive waste and radioactive waste repositories Map: Radwaste repositories in the exclusion zone.

          In preparation of the maps of contamination of the territory of Ukraine observation data have been used. These data have been obtained in the framework of the program of more precise definition of the radiological status of the territory of Ukraine after the accident at Chornobyl NPP carried out during 1986-1995 by radiological departments of different ministries and authorities (The State Committee of Ukraine for Hydrometeorology, the State Committee of Ukraine on Geology, Ministry of Agriculture of Ukraine, Ministry of Health of Ukraine, Academy of Medical Sciences, National Academy of Sciences and others). Apart of it the data of aerial gamma survey of the most contaminated regions of Ukrainian Polissya including woodlands have been used. Used sets of data are more complete as compared with the data used for preparation of contamination maps earlier [13, 14].

          Several big settlements on the territory of Ukraine have been significantly contaminated by radionuclides as a result of the accident: Prypiat, Chornobyl, Korosten. Residents of Prypiat and Chornobyl have been evacuated during the first days after the accident. Local spots with high contamination level have been detected in the city Korosten after thorough survey. These spots have been decontaminated. Relatively high levels of cesium-137 are still observed in the northern part of Korosten. During construction of the Slavutych city radiological situation on its territory has significantly improved. Only in adjacent forests on the elevations contamination by cesium-137 is observed. This contamination reaches 120-150 kBq/m2. The maps of contamination of Korosten and Slavutych by cesium-137 - Map: Contamination of the territories by cesium-137 (according to materials of aerial gamma survey), Korosten city, Map: Contamination of the territories by cesium-137 (according to materials of aerial gamma survey), Slavutych city. These maps have been prepared using the results of aerial gamma spectrometry surveys carried out in 1994-1997 by aerial geophysical department of Production Association “Pivnichukrgeology” to order of the Ministry of Chornobyl (since 1996 - the Ministry of Emergency Situations of Ukraine).

          Literature
          1.Reference book on agrochemical and agroecological status of soils in Ukraine. - K., 1994.
          2.Israel Yu.A. Chernobyl: Radioactive contamination of natural environment. – Leningrad: Hydrometeoizdat, 1990. – 296 p.
          3.Nuclear encyclopaedia/ edited by A. Yaroshynskaya - M., 1996.
          4.Chornobyl catastrophe / edited by V.G. Baryakhtar. - K.: Naukova dumka, 1996. - 576 p.
          5.Gaidar O.V., Tabachnyi L.Ya., Fursa A.D., Chornomorets N.F. Influence of landscape factors on formation of radionuclide contamination field of exclusion zone and adjacent to Chornobyl NPP territories // Newsletter of ecological status of exclusion and compulsory relocation zone. – 2000. - ? 15. - p. 58-61.
          6.Chernobyl: Ten Year On. Radiological and health impact. An appraisal by the NEA Committee on Radiation Protection and Public Health. NEA, November 1995, modified figure from Summary report on the post accident review meeting of the Chernobyl accident. Safety series No. 75, INSAG-1, IAEA, Vienna, 1996.
          7.Sivintsev Yu.V., Khrulev A.A. Assessment of radioactive discharge during the accident of 1986 at 4th unit of Chernobyl nuclear power plant//Nuclear energy. – 1995. –Vol.78. – Issue 6. - p. 403-417.
          8.Begichev, S. et al. Radioactive releases due to Chernobyl accident. Fission product transport processes in reactor accidents. Ed. J T Rogers. Hemisphere, 1990.
          9.Devell, L., Guntay, S. and Powers, D.: The Chernobyl reactor accident sourse term: Development of a consensus view. CSNI report of NEA/OECD, 1995.
          10.Buzulukov, Yu. and Dobrynin, Yu. "Release of radionuclides during the Chernobyl accident". The Chernobyl papers. Ed. Merwin, S. and Baolonov, M. Reseach Enterprises, Richland WA, Vol. 1, 1993. pp. 3-21.
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>contents</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the territory of Ukraine by cesium-137 (as of July 1, 1985)</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_70/ref_24088287_091098_70.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the territory of Ukraine by strontium-90 (as of July 1, 1985)</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_72/ref_24088287_091098_72.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the territory of Ukraine by cesium-137 (as of May 10, 1986)</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_105/ref_24088287_091098_105.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the territory of Ukraine by cesium-137 (as of May 10, 2014)</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_118/ref_24088287_091098_118.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the territory of Ukraine by strontium-90 (as of May 10, 1986)</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_107/ref_24088287_091098_107.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the territory of Ukraine by strontium-90 (as of May 10, 2014)</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_119/ref_24088287_091098_119.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the territory of Ukraine by plutonium isotopes</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_20/ref_24088287_091098_20.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Prediction of contamination of the territory of Ukraine by americium-241 for 2056</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_22/ref_24088287_091098_22.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the exclusion zone by cesium-137 (as of May 10, 1986)</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_109/ref_24088287_091098_109.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the exclusion zone by cesium-137 (as of May 10, 2014)</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_120/ref_24088287_091098_120.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the exclusion zone by strontium-90 (as of May 10, 1986)</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_111/ref_24088287_091098_111.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the exclusion zone by strontium-90 (as of May 10, 2014)</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_121/ref_24088287_091098_121.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the exclusion zone by plutonium isotopes</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_33/ref_24088287_091098_33.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the exclusion zone by americium-241</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_34/ref_24088287_091098_34.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Prediction of contamination of the exclusion zone by americium-241 for 2056</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_79/ref_24088287_091098_79.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the territories by cesium-137 (according to materials of aerial gamma survey), Korosten city</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_49/ref_24088287_091098_49.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Contamination of the territories by cesium-137 (according to materials of aerial gamma survey), Slavutych city</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_71/ref_24088287_091098_71.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Radwaste repositories in the exclusion zone</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_37/ref_24088287_091098_37.htm</link>
        <indexedWords></indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
    </branch>

    <branch id="b02">
      <branchText>Section II. Irradiation of population and medical consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe</branchText>
      <branchDescription></branchDescription>
      <link></link>
      <indexedWords></indexedWords>
      <Frame>contents</Frame>
      <ImageIndex>0</ImageIndex>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Irradiation of population and medical consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Documents/part2_eng.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>Accident at Chornobyl nuclear power plant caused the most significant transboundary radioactive contamination of environment in the history of mankind. After-accident status is characterized by large-scale and multi-component structure of irradiation of population consisting of:
•external gamma irradiation from radioactive fallout to the soil;
•internal irradiation caused by consumption of the food contaminated mainly by cesium and strontium.
•irradiation of thyroid gland by radioiodine;
•irradiation by transuranium elements.

Depending on the type and duration of irradiation suffered population is split in the following groups:
•people that participated in the liquidation of the accident at Chornobyl nuclear power plant.
•residents evacuated from Prypiat and other settlements of exclusion zone.
•residents living on the radioactively contaminated territories;
•children born in 1968-1986 with irradiated thyroid gland.

Representatives of different regions and settlements of Ukraine and other republics of FSU took part in the liquidation of accident consequences. Evacuated from the exclusion zone people have been resettled over the whole territory of Ukraine. Demographic differences in the number and structure of liquidators and people relocated from contaminated zone are conditioned in the majority by intentions of the law makers to increase the level of social protection of sufferers rather than by radiological factors. Map showing the distribution of these groups of population on the territory of Ukraine is presented on the Карта: Чисельність і склад громадян, які мають статус постраждалих внаслідок Чорнобильської катастрофи.

Impact of the catastrophe on population caused by exposure to the radioiodine lasted during the first two months after the accident. Due to physiological differences there is an age dependence of irradiation dose caused by radioiodine: the highest doses got the children born in 1986, others children doses gradually decreased with the age by the moment of accident. Adult population got insignificant radiation doses as compared with children. Maps of thyroid gland irradiation are presented for seven age groups – starting from the children under 1 year of age at the moment of accident (first age group) until the adult population (seventh age group). Maps of the territory of Ukraine are presented on a scale 1:5 000 000 (Карта: Дози опромінення щитовидної залози. Перша вікова група (до 1 року на момент аварії), Карта: Дози опромінення щитовидної залози. Друга вікова група (від 1 до 3 років на момент аварії), Карта: Дози опромінення щитовидної залози. Третя вікова група (від 4 до 7 років на момент аварії), Карта: Дози опромінення щитовидної залози. Четверта вікова група (від 8 до 11 років на момент аварії), Карта: Дози опромінення щитовидної залози. П'ята вікова група (від 12 до 15 років на момент аварії), Карта: Дози опромінення щитовидної залози. Шоста вікова група (від 16 до 18 років на момент аварії), Карта: Дози опромінення щитовидної залози. Сьома вікова група (старші 18 років на момент аварії)). Calculations of thyroid gland irradiation doses have been executed according to the methodology Calculations of thyroid gland irradiation doses have been executed according to the methodology [9].

Population living on the territories enrolled in radioactively contaminated zones as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe was exposed and still is exposed to external and internal irradiation. Dosimeteric passportization of the settlements is carried out since 1991 to ensure assessment of the impact of this irradiation on population. One of the tasks of dosimetric passportization is assessment of passport and reference doses of irradiation of population. Passport irradiation dose is a calculated effective (equivalent) dose of human irradiation. 

Passport dose is one of key criteria of zoning of radioactively contaminated territories [10]. Calculations of passport dose have been executed according to the methodologies of National Commission on Radiation Protection [9, 11]. 

Passport dose includes the following components:
•external gamma irradiation conditioned by radioactive fallout on the Earth surface.
•internal irradiation by radioisotopes of cesium, strontium and transuranium elements.
•industrial irradiation (in the vicinity of operating NPPs).

During the late phase after the accident at Chornobyl NPP the external gamma irradiation dose was formed mainly by radioisotopes of cesium, first of all cesium-137. During the initial phase after the accident the dose has been formed by not less than 19 radionuclides and radioisotopes of niobium, zirconium, iodine, lanthanum, barium made the main contribution. But in aggregate cesium radioisotopes made 70% contribution to the dose obtained from external gamma irradiation during the whole time span after the accident.

Internal irradiation during the activity of accidental source has been caused mainly by cesium radioisotopes. Irradiation by strontium radioisotope during the first twenty years after Chornobyl accident was 7-10 times less and by transuranium elements tens of times less than by cesium radioisotopes (both by average annual dose rate and by doses accumulated during different time spans).

Methodology for calculation of passport and predicted irradiation doses for settlements enrolled in the radioactive contamination zones is presented in respective methodological guides [9, 11]. Doses for 2161 settlements have been calculated according to these guides. For other settlements where dosimetric passportization has not been performed the dose values have been calculated following the methodology for assessment of retrospective-predictive irradiation doses based on the system of referential functions, relations and parameters that by-turn reconstruct the most generic and universal regularities for the whole territory including lognormal law for distribution of used referential values.

"Referential" values characterizing the radioecological situation in a settlement are the densities of radioactive contamination of soil by cesium-137, strontium-90 and plutonium-239, -240, averaged for territories of settlement and its vicinity. Coefficients of transition of cesium-137 from soil to milk also have been considered as well as a proportion of activities of main discharged gamma emitters in the fallouts (presented as of 26.04.86). Cesium-137 transition coefficient will be changed insignificantly during the next years. Highest transition coefficients are inherent to organogenic (peat) soils with excessive water saturation mostly found on the north east of Ukraine . These coefficients are in tens and even hundreds times more than in mineral soils (see soil map on Карта: Ґрунти). For strontium-90 the speed of migration deep down is lower or comparable by profile with cesium-137. Cesium radioisotopes taken with contaminated food have a dominant contribution to internal irradiation of population. The main dose-forming product is milk produced in private sector. Levels of cesium in milk can differ in several times even within the same settlement. Weather conditions have significant influence of the content of radionuclides. Cesium content in milk is higher during rainy years rather than during the dry ones. Therefore the maps on milk contamination are variable in space and in time. Milk contamination level trends show decrease with the years and are is presented on the maps with annual averages by the results of sampling taken in the most contaminated areas Карта: Вміст цезію-137 у молоці (середньорічні значення для найбільш постраждалих районів, 1991-2005 роки).

To prepare the measures on liquidation of catastrophe consequences and minimization of population irradiation levels it is important to assess not only the part of the dose already received by population but also the dose they would receive in future when living on contaminated territories. Map of retrospective total effective irradiation doses received by population for 20 years (1986-2006) is presented on Карта: Cумарні ефективні дози зовнішнього та внутрішнього (від радіоізотопів цезію, стронцію та трансуранових елементів) опромінення, розраховані на період 1986-2006 роки (20 років після аварії), map of predictive total effective irradiation doses for 70 years (1986-2055) is shown on Карта: Cумарні ефективні дози зовнішнього та внутрішнього (від радіоізотопів цезію, стронцію та трансуранових елементів) опромінення, розраховані на період 1986-2055 роки (70 років після аварії). Total doses are calculated considering the values of passport and retrospective-predictive doses for separate years. For 25 years after the accident the zone of settlements has been formed on the territory of Ukraine where received irradiation doses exceed 10 and even 50 mSv. Insignificant increasing of this dose on 5-10 mSv and in many cases less than on 1 mSv will be observed during next decades. Doses received by population for 25 years practically coincide with data for 20 years. Distribution of settlements by dose value for 70 years not significantly differs from the distribution for 20 years and in many cases even for 12 years. Therefore application of such measures of accident consequences minimization as relocation and resettlement is not justified anymore since population already got the main part of Chornobyl irradiation on contaminated territories during the first years after the accident and expenses related to resettlement are inadequate to potential harm caused by excessive irradiation in case if people stay on this territory.

Determination of statistically significant impact of irradiation on the morbidity of people is one of the main tasks for studies of accident consequences. It is supposed that the most sensitive factor of this impact is increasing of oncological diseases among suffered population. Multiple factors and details pertaining to this problem do not allow constructing spatial distribution of a number of oncological diseases conditioned by Chornobyl accident. Assessments of risks related to radio-induced malignant tumors occurred among population suffered as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe are more correct. Summarized values of these assessments are presented in table 2.1. 

Table 2.1. Assessment of absolute and relative radiation risk related to Chornobyl irradiation for population of radioactively contaminated territories of Ukraine for 12 years after the accident [12]




Irradiation value (mSv per person)
 

0.5
 

0.5-1
 

1-2
 

2-5
 

5-10
 

10-20
 

20-50
 

50-70
 

70-100
 

100
 

Total
 


Population of 
contaminated 
territories
 

Thous. people
 
1.2
 
2.6
 
94.8
 
1008.2
 
568.3
 
465.0
 
209.6
 
19.3
 
1.6
 
1.2
 
2371.8
 


In per cents
 
0.05
 
0.11
 
4.0
 
42.5
 
24.0
 
19.6
 
8.8
 
0.81
 
0.07
 
0.05
 
100
 


Absolute risk
 (occurrences)
 
0.02
 
0.07
 
4.4
 
96.8
 
115.7
 
237.1
 
2499.4
 
38.1
 
4.5
 
4.6
 
751
 


Spontaneous level 
(occurrences)
 
47
 
104
 
3792
 
40329
 
22732
 
18599
 
8383
 
772
 
66
 
50
 
94874
 


Relative risk (*10-3)
 
0.33
 
0.69
 
1.2
 
2.4
 
5.1
 
12.8
 
29.8
 
49.3
 
68.0
 
93.5
 
7.9
 


Percentage of
 Chornobyl cancers
 
0.03
 
0.07
 
0.12
 
0.24
 
0.51
 
1.26
 
2.89
 
4.70
 
6.37
 
8.55
 
0.79
 
 

Average spontaneous level of lethal oncological diseases in Ukraine is 2000 per year per one million of population [12], whereas estimated absolute spontaneous level in irradiated subpopulation for 12 years after the accidents equals 94.8 thousand occurrences. Chornobyl factor adds to spontaneous level less than 0.8% (751 cases). Despite the fact that increasing of Chornobyl cancers for studied contingent is not observed statistically for those subgroups having received individual dose more than 100 mSv and more the local increase for 12 years can reach 10%. Comprehensive data characterizing the influence of Chornobyl accident on general values of population morbidity are published in the special references [13, 18]. Analysis of medical monitoring system in Ukraine, trends and character of influence of irradiation on different categories of suffered population are also presented in these books.

There are two classifications of suffered people. Social classification has been established in national legislation in 1991 (see section III). Medical classification has been introduced by the Ministry of Health of USSR and it is still in force in Ukraine. According to medical classification citizens exposed to radiation resulted from the accident at Chornobyl NPP are divided into four groups of primary accounting. First accounting group consists of the persons participated in the works on liquidation of the accident at Chornobyl NPP or its consequences in exclusion zone. Second group consists of the people evacuated from exclusion zone. Third group consists of the people living on the territories enrolled in radioactive contamination zones (according to actual legislation). Fourth group consists of the children born from those enrolled in the 1-3 groups of primary accounting.

Information on the health status of population is being collected in the framework of permanent medical monitoring and is input in the medical sub-register of National register of population suffered as a result of the accident at Chornobyl NPP. Main issues of monitoring of the health status of suffered population are regulated by articles 16, 17 of the Law of Ukraine "On Status and Social Protection of Population Suffered from Chornobyl Catastrophe" [14]. Issues of organization and functioning of State (National) register is regulated by relevant Provisions [15].

Ukrainian military register and its sections supported by the Ministry of Defense of Ukraine, Ministry of Internal Affairs of Ukraine and Security Service of Ukraine are constituent part of State register. Analysis of medical statistical data is regularly published in scientific publications of medical and biological profile [13, 18], National reports of Ukraine [17, 19]. Materials of the Center of Medical Statistics of the Ministry of Health of Ukraine [13, 18] have been used as a basis for statistical maps of population morbidity, structure of general morbidity, prevalence of diseases among suffered population and structures of prevalence of diseases among suffered population as a result of the accident at Chornobyl NPP Карта: Поширеність захворювань серед дорослих і підлітків 1, 2, 3 груп первинного обліку, Карта: Захворюваність серед дорослих і підлітків 1, 2, 3 груп первинного обліку, Карта: Поширеність захворювань серед дітей до 14 років 2, 3, 4 груп первинного обліку, Карта: Захворюваність серед дітей до 14 років 2, 3, 4 груп первинного обліку. Maps have been designed for territories of twelve suffered regions of Ukraine, age categories “adults and adolescents” (1-3 groups of primary accounting) and “children” (4th group of primary accounting).

In general available monitoring data and its cartographical interpretation indicate on the presence of certain trend regarding the negative impact of radioactive contamination on the health of people by the data of morbidity of population suffered as a result of the accident at Chornobyl NPP. Conclusions and problems related to assessment of this impact are presented in mentioned publications [12, 13, 18] and in [16, 17, 19] and other scientific publications.

Maps of the section have been developed by the following group of authors: I.A. Likhtaryov, V.V. Berkovsky, I.A. Kairo, L.M. Kovgan, V.M. Shpak, L.Ya. Tabachnyi, O.Ye. Lytvynenko, S.V. Davydchuk, V.I. Reshetnyk, O.R. Savchuk, S.O. Sotnikov.

I.A. Likhtaryov, L.M. Kovgan, L.Ya. Tabachnyi, O.Ye. Lytvynenko, O.R. Savchuk
</indexedWords>
        <Frame>contents</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>

      <branch id="b0101">
        <branchText>Thyroid gland irradiation dose</branchText>
        <branchDescription />
        <link></link>
        <indexedWords></indexedWords>
        <Frame>contents</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>2</ImageIndex>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Thyroid gland irradiation dose. First age group (under 1 year at the moment of accident)</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Maps/24088287_091098_25_gr1/ref_24088287_091098_25_gr1.htm</link>
          <indexedWords>Thyroid gland irradiation doses, cGy</indexedWords>
          <Frame>script</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Thyroid gland irradiation dose. Second age group (from 1 to 3 years at the moment of accident)</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Maps/24088287_091098_25_gr2/ref_24088287_091098_25_gr2.htm</link>
          <indexedWords>Thyroid gland irradiation doses, cGy</indexedWords>
          <Frame>script</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Thyroid gland irradiation dose. Third age group (from 4 to 7 years at the moment of accident)</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Maps/24088287_091098_25_gr3/ref_24088287_091098_25_gr3.htm</link>
          <indexedWords>Thyroid gland irradiation doses, cGy</indexedWords>
          <Frame>script</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Thyroid gland irradiation dose. Fourth age group (from 8 to 11 years at the moment of accident)</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Maps/24088287_091098_25_gr4/ref_24088287_091098_25_gr4.htm</link>
          <indexedWords>Thyroid gland irradiation doses, cGy</indexedWords>
          <Frame>script</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Thyroid gland irradiation dose. Fifth age group (from 12 to 15 years at the moment of accident)</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Maps/24088287_091098_25_gr5/ref_24088287_091098_25_gr5.htm</link>
          <indexedWords>Thyroid gland irradiation doses, cGy</indexedWords>
          <Frame>script</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Thyroid gland irradiation dose. Sixth age group (from 16 to 18 years at the moment of accident)</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Maps/24088287_091098_25_gr6/ref_24088287_091098_25_gr6.htm</link>
          <indexedWords>Thyroid gland irradiation doses, cGy</indexedWords>
          <Frame>script</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Thyroid gland irradiation dose. Seventh age group (older 18 year at the moment of accident)</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Maps/24088287_091098_25_gr7/ref_24088287_091098_25_gr7.htm</link>
          <indexedWords>Thyroid gland irradiation doses, cGy</indexedWords>
          <Frame>script</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
      </branch>

      <leaf>
        <leafText>Content of cesium-137 in milk (average annual values for the most suffered regions, 1991-2005)</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_27/ref_24088287_091098_27.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Content of cesium-137 in milk, Bq/l
          The number of samples taken
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Total effective doses for external and internal (caused by radioisotopes cesium, strontium and transuranium elements) irradiation, calculated for 1986-2006 (20 years after the accident)</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_26_abs20/ref_24088287_091098_26_abs20.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>Irradiation doses, mSv</indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Total effective doses for external and internal (caused by radioisotopes cesium, strontium and transuranium elements) irradiation, calculated for 1986-2055 (70 years after the accident)</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_26_abs70/ref_24088287_091098_26_abs70.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>Irradiation doses, mSv</indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Morbidity prevalence among adults and adolescents of 1, 2, 3 groups of primary accounting</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_62/ref_24088287_091098_62.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Morbidity prevalence among adults and adolescents of 1, 2, 3 groups, per 10 000,
          Morbidity prevalence among adults and adolescents, per 10 000
          Part of preventively examined adults and adolescents of 1, 2, 3 groups,

          Morbidity prevalence, per 10 000 suffered people, infectious and parasitic diseases
          - neoplasms
          - endocrine system diseases, malnutrition, metabolic disorder
          - diseases of blood and hemopoietic organs
          - mental insanity
          - nervous system diseases
          - hearing diseases
          - circulatory system diseases
          - respiratory diseases
          - digestive diseases

        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Morbidity among adults and adolescents of 1, 2, 3 groups of primary accounting</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_60/ref_24088287_091098_60.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Morbidity among adults and adolescents of 1, 2, 3 groups, per 10 000
          Morbidity among adults and adolescents of region, per 10 000
          Part of acknowledged ill people among examined children of 2, 3, 4 groups, %, 2005
          Morbidity, per 10 000 suffered people, infectious and parasitic diseases
          - neoplasms
          - endocrine system diseases, malnutrition, metabolic disorder
          - diseases of blood and hemopoietic organs
          - mental insanity
          - nervous system diseases
          - hearing diseases
          - circulatory system diseases
          - respiratory diseases
          - digestive diseases
          - urogenital diseases
          - diseases of skin and subcutaneous fat
          - diseases of the musculoskeletal system and connective tissue
          - congenital anomalies
          - symptoms, signs, inaccurately determined statuses
          - traumas and intoxication
          - total, except respiratory
          diseases
          - total
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Morbidity prevalence among children under 14 of 2, 3, 4 groups of primary accounting</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_63/ref_24088287_091098_63.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Morbidity prevalence among children under 14 of 2, 3, 4 groups, per 10 000
          Morbidity prevalence among children under 14, per 10 000
          Part of preventively examined children under 14 of 2, 3, 4 groups, %, 2005

          Morbidity prevalence, per 1 000 suffered people, infectious and parasitic diseases
          - neoplasms
          - endocrine system diseases, malnutrition, metabolic disorder
          - diseases of blood and hemopoietic organs
          - mental insanity
          - nervous system diseases
          - hearing diseases
          - circulatory system diseases
          - respiratory diseases
          - digestive diseases
          - urogenital diseases
          - diseases of skin and subcutaneous fat
          - diseases of the musculoskeletal system and connective tissue
          - congenital anomalies
          - particular statuses occurring in the perinatal period
          - symptoms, signs, inaccurately determined statuses
          - traumas and intoxication
          - total
          - total, except respiratory
          diseases

        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Morbidity among children under 14 of 2, 3, 4 groups of primary accounting</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_61/ref_24088287_091098_61.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Morbidity among children under 14 of 2, 3, 4 groups, per 10 000
          Morbidity among children under 14, per 10 000
          Part of acknowledged ill people among examined children of 2, 3, 4 groups
          Morbidity, per 1 000 suffered people, infectious and parasitic diseases
          - neoplasms
          - endocrine system diseases, malnutrition, metabolic disorder
          - diseases of blood and hemopoietic organs
          - mental insanity
          - nervous system diseases
          - hearing diseases
          - circulatory system diseases
          - respiratory diseases
          - digestive diseases
          - urogenital diseases
          - diseases of skin and subcutaneous fat
          - diseases of the musculoskeletal system and connective tissue
          - congenital anomalies
          - particular statuses occurring in the perinatal period
          - symptoms, signs, inaccurately determined statuses
          - traumas and intoxication
          - total
          - total, except respiratory
          diseases
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
    </branch>

    <branch id="b03">
      <branchText>Section III. Social and economical consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe</branchText>
      <branchDescription></branchDescription>
      <link></link>
      <indexedWords></indexedWords>
      <Frame>contents</Frame>
      <ImageIndex>0</ImageIndex>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Social and economical consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Documents/part3_eng.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          As a result of Chornobyl catastrophe majority of the territory of Ukraine has been radioactively contaminated. Population of separate northern areas has received and continues to receive significant doses of extra ionizing irradiation caused by consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe. Ukrainian legislation envisages social protection of population suffered as a result of the accident. Laws of Ukraine "On Status and Social Protection of Population Suffered from Chornobyl Catastrophe” [20] and “On legal regime of radioactively contaminated territory as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe" [21] are determinative in this regard.

          In the Law [20] emphasizes that “Chornobyl catastrophe had the influence on the life of millions of people. New social and economical conditions have been developed in region. Ukraine has been declared an ecological disaster zone. Establishment of the system of reliable protection from the consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe require allocation of significant financial, material and intellectual resources”. The maps presenting social and economical problems caused by Chornobyl catastrophe are presented in this section of the Atlas.

          In accordance with the Article 2 of the Law [20] Ukraine has the territories attributed as zones of radioactive contamination:

          Depending on landscape and geochemical features of soils, excess of natural pre-catastrophe level of radionuclides accumulation in environment, levels of possible negative influence on health of population connected with them, requirements regarding radioactive protection of population and other social measures, taking into consideration general production and social everyday relations the territory affected by radionuclide contamination as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe is divided into zones. These zones are:


          1) exclusion zone is the territory where evacuation of population has been carried out in 1986;

          2) compulsory relocation zone is the territory intensively contaminated by long-lived radionuclides with soil contamination density exceeding levels before the accident by cesium isotopes from 15.0 Кі/km2 and more, or by strontium from 3.0 Ki/km2 and more, or by plutonium from 0.1 Ki/km2 and more, where calculated effective equivalent irradiation dose of people taking into account coefficients of migration of radionuclides to plants and other factors can exceed 5.0 mSv (0.5 rem) per year over the dose, that they would receive before the accident;

          3) Guaranteed voluntary relocation zone is the territory with soil contamination density exceeding levels before the accident by cesium isotopes from 5.0 Кі/кm2 to 15.0 Кі/km2, or by strontium from 0.15 to 3.0 Ki/km2, or by plutonium from 0.01 to 0.1 Ki/km2, where calculated effective equivalent irradiation dose of people taking into account coefficients of migration of radionuclides to plants and other factors can exceed 1.0 mSv (0.1 rem) per year over the dose, that they would receive before the accident;

          4) Zone of thorough radioecological control is the territory with soil contamination density exceeding levels before the accident by cesium isotopes from 1.0 Кі/кm2 to 5.0 Кі/km2, or by strontium from 0.02 to 0.15 Ki/km2, or by plutonium from 0.005 to 0.01 Ki/km2, where calculated effective equivalent irradiation dose of people taking into account coefficients of migration of radionuclides to plants and other factors can exceed 0.5 mSv (0.05 rem) per year over the dose, that they would receive before the accident (second part of Article 2 in edition of the Law №2532-12 of 01.07.92)”.

          List of settlements enrolled in contamination zones is determined by a series of legislative acts of Ukraine [22, 27, 28, 29]. Altogether 2 293 settlements having population 2,155.1 thousand people including 460.6 thousand children under 17 are enrolled in contaminated zones. Area of the territory of contaminated zones is 52.9 thousand km2, including 24.7 thousand km2 of forests.

          In accordance with Article 2 of the Law [21] the main criteria of enrolling the settlements to respective zone has to be a calculated effective equivalent irradiation dose of people. In 1991 at the time of approval of the decree of the Council of Ministers of Ukrainian SSR [22] comprehensive dosimetric passportization of settlements on the radioactively contaminated territories had not been finished. Therefore almost 1300 settlements have been enrolled in respective contaminated zones by soil contamination levels. Zoning map of the territory of Ukraine according to actual legislation is presented on Карта: Зонування радіоактивно забрудненої території України згідно чинних нормативно-правових актів. After completion of dosimetric passportization carried out during subsequent years it has been found that contamination levels and values of passport doses give different results and it can be easily determined comparing the maps of contamination (see section I) and dosimentric maps (see section II). It is explained by the fact that for the prevailing part of contaminated territories the present landscape and geochemical conditions determine relatively insignificant coefficients of transition of radionuclides to food and further intake by human body. If dose criterion is used as a basis then content and boundaries of zones can be significantly changed. The map with the draft zone boundaries by dose criterion is presented on Карта: Проект зонування радіоактивно забрудненої території України за даними дозиметричної паспортизації. Comparative characteristics of actual contaminated zones and contaminated zones by dose criterion are presented in table 3.1.

          Table 3.1. - Comparative characteristics of contaminated zones (actual and according to zoning by dose criterion)


          1)As of January 1, 2007.

          Social protection of population suffered as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe is a priority of state policy in overcoming the consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe. According to actual legislation of Ukraine people suffered as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe get about 50 types of assistance, benefits and compensations. In accordance with the Law [20] suffered population is grouped on participants of liquidation of accident at Chornobyl NPP, people suffered as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe, children considered as those who suffered as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe and persons not enrolled in these categories but having the right on benefits according to Article 24 of the Law [20]. Benefits will be provided to families in connection with the loss of a breadwinner in case if this death is connected with Chornobyl catastrophe. According to data of State Statistics Committee of Ukraine and Ministry of Ukraine of Emergencies and Affairs of Population Protection from the Consequences of Chornobyl Catastrophe [23, 24] size of suffered population in Ukraine as of January 1, 2007 was 2 526 2 thousands, including liquidators – 297.85 thousands, suffered – 1 636.3 thousands, children – 589.45 thousands, suffered but not enrolled in the categories – 2.59 thousands, families getting benefits in connection with the loss of a breadwinner – 20 89 thousands. Map showing distribution of suffered population by regions of Ukraine is presented on Карта: Чисельність і склад громадян, які мають статус постраждалих внаслідок Чорнобильської катастрофи

          Total expenses related with liquidation of the accident at Chornobyl NPP and losses connected with the accident are being increased every year. Complexity of these determinations is related to the fact that the main activities aimed at liquidation of accident consequence have been carried out at times of USSR and first years of independence of Ukraine during economical recession and significant inflation processes. As compared to the first years after the accident when the majority of financial means have been spent on capital construction the share of funds allocated for social protection of population during the last years has been significantly increased and share of costs for social protection forms about 85% (table 3.2). Largest part of expenditures is aimed at financing in the frame of the articles "compensation payment and benefits providing” and “providing of benefits for pension provision and assistance”. According to calculations financing of social protection activities in line with all articles of the Law would require more than 60 billion hryvnyas. Execution of plan of 2007 was about 100% (in 1998 - 53.8%, in 1999 - 92.2%).

          Table 3.2. - expense items of the State budget of Ukraine aimed at liquidation of consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe in 2001 - 2010 [25].
          Payment of compensations, providing benefits, social insurance 976406 1559071 64.38 73.94
          Providing benefits for pension provisions and assistance 583203 * * *
          State capital investment 99700 15000
          ** 218  6.57 0.71
          Self-selective relocation of people from radioactively contaminated territories and construction of dwellings for people enrolled in category I of suffered people 17000 66462 1.12 3.15
          Implementation of measures at “Shelter” and decommissioning of ChNPP 280500 355826 18.50 16.88
          Comprehensive medical and sanitary services for suffered population 73000 40000
          ** 94406 4.81 1.90
          Radiological protection of population and sanitation of radioactively contaminated environment 39390 44970 2.60 2.13
          Scientific support of activities and information systems 12000 12743  0.79 0.60
          10000 10716 0.66 0.51
          Incidental expenses (reserve) 5500 0 0.36 0
          Execution of separate measures by all-Ukrainian public organization “Union of Chornobyl of Ukraine” and other public organizations working in social protection of population suffered from consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe 1000 1000 0.07 0.05
          Information of public on the issues related to liquidation of consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe 2000 2800 0.13 0.13

          *** Total

          1516496

          2108588




          Expenses of general fund of State budget of Ukraine 32 597 824 161 819 000
          Share of “Chornobyl” expenses in expenses of general fund of State budget of Ukraine 4.65% 1.30%


          Notes:

          1. * - assignment to Pension fund in accordance with the Law of Ukraine “On State Budget of Ukraine for 2011” are not split on separate programs, including – share for pension provision of per sons suffered as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe, is not eanmarked [25];

          2. ** - additional funding at the expense of special fund of State budget of Ukraine, charge for the RAW;

          3. *** - not accounting for expenses on pension provision of persons suffered as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe and expenses of special fund of State budget of Ukraine.

          As a result of contamination of environment by radionuclides of Chornobyl discharge significant part of the territory of Ukraine became uninhabitable. Inhabitants from settlements enrolled in the exclusion zone of radioactive contamination have been evacuated completely, and 2nd zones of radioactive contamination – have been resettled mostly. Map on Карта: Міграції населення із забруднених територій presents distribution of total amount of resettled people and locations of compact relocation of suffered people in rural area. Data from [26] have been used during preparation of this map.

          Maps of the section have been developed by the following group of authors: L.Ya. Tabachnyi, S.V. Davydchuk, V.I. Reshetnyk, O.R. Savchuk, G.Ye. Sotnikova.
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>contents</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Density of population of Ukraine</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_55/ref_24088287_091098_55.htm</link>
        <indexedWords></indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Zoning of radioactively contaminated territory of Ukraine according to actual regulations</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_58/ref_24088287_091098_58.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>Radioactive contamination zone</indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Draft zoning of radioactively contaminated territory of Ukraine according to dosimetric passportization data</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_66/ref_24088287_091098_66.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Radioactive contamination zone
          Dosimetric passportization data
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Number and composition of citizens having the status of suffered as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe </leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_57fnum/ref_24088287_091098_57fnum.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Total number of actual population, thousand people
          Total number of suffered people
          Total number of suffered people per 1000 population, persons
          Relevance of data
          Liquidators of consequences of the accident at Chornobyl, category 1, persons
          Liquidators of consequences of the accident at Chornobyl, category 2, persons
          Liquidators of consequences of the accident at Chornobyl, category 3, persons
          Suffered from Chornobyl catastrophe, category 1, persons
          Suffered from Chornobyl catastrophe, category 2, persons
          Suffered from Chornobyl catastrophe, category 3, persons
          Suffered from Chornobyl catastrophe, category 4, persons
          Persons not enrolled in the categories but having the right on benefits, persons
          Children considered as suffered as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe, persons
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Improvement of health of children suffered as a result of Chornobyl catastrophe</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_89/ref_24088287_091098_89.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Region
          Number of children that participated in health improvement measures, persons, total, 1996
          - 1997
          - 1998
          - 1999
          - 2000
          - 2002
          - 2003
          - 2004
          - 2005
          Number of children that participated in health improvement measures, persons, country camps, 1996
          - 1997
          - 1998
          - 1999
          - 2000
          - 2002
          - 2003
          - 2004
          - 2005
          Number of children that participated in health improvement measures, persons, camps sanatorium, 1996
          - 1997
          - 1998
          - 1999
          - 2000
          - 2002
          - 2003
          - 2004
          - 2005
          Number of institutions participating in health-improving of suffered children, total
          - including the country camps
          - including camps sanatorium
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Migration of population from contaminated territories</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_59/ref_24088287_091098_59.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Radioactive contamination zone
          Zone of radioactive contamination, dosimetric passportization data
          Cottages/apartments
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Construction program aimed at liquidation of consequences of Chornobyl catastrophe in 1996-2000 </leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_65/ref_24088287_091098_65.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Region
          Disbursement of the limit of state centralized investments, thousands hryvnyas, 1996
          - 1997
          - 1998
          - 1999
          - 2000
          Disbursement of investments, production purpose, thousands hryvnyas, 1996
          - 1997
          - 1998
          - 1999
          - 2000
          Disbursement of investments, nonproduction purpose, thousands hryvnyas, 1996
          - 1997
          - 1998
          - 1999
          - 2000
          Implementation of contractual works, thousands hryvnyas, 2000
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
    </branch>

    <branch id="b04">
      <branchText>Section IV. Reference data</branchText>
      <branchDescription></branchDescription>
      <link></link>
      <indexedWords></indexedWords>
      <Frame>contents</Frame>
      <ImageIndex>0</ImageIndex>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Reference data</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Documents/part4_eng.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Methodology of preparation of radioactive contamination maps of the territory

          Formation of the field of radioactive contamination of the territory is conditioned by a number of factors first of all by dynamics and spectrum of discharged radionuclides and meteorological conditions (Section I).

          On condition of precise reconstruction of spatiotemporal map of air flows it is possible to determine quite precise structure of the field and take into account field anisotropy choosing the methodology of preparation of maps. However approach based on antecedent determination of the structure of contamination field has a number of shortcomings. Field macrostructure can be considered as clearly determined only for western trace. For other traces the field structure is fuzzy. Data representing meteorological conditions at time of formation of contamination field are less precise and representative than direct observation data of this field. The latter can be updated as a result of new measurements while information on meteorological conditions can be updated only using mathematical simulation methods. This problem is even more complicated since set of flows determines the character of fallouts ambiguously and depends on the mesoscale level factors – status of atmospheric boundary layer, precipitation, landscape etc. For the majority of mentioned factors only qualitative assessments of influence are known of those that could be used for clarification of the structure of contamination field. Some quantitative assessments of the influence of mentioned factors are less precise than direct measurements. In general field have been formed during several phases as a superposition of fallouts separated in time. Therefore the field structure is more complicated, heterogeneous and utilization of information on the influence of other factors on mapping becomes more difficult.

          Hundreds of thousands of contamination levels measurements have been executed on separate spots or surface patches after the accident at Chornobyl NPP. For mapping of contamination maps the values of field contamination levels on separate spots have to be expanded to adjacent territories. Different interpolation methods are often used for reconstruction of continuous variable fields by separate dimensions. Majority of these methods are realized in available commercial geostatic packages and geoinformation software tools. For mapping of contamination maps it was necessary to determine the sequence of the tasks on data processing and preparation, data interpolation and mapping, its verification and editing. Both formal algorithmic methods and methods with utilization of expert assessments have been used while executing these tasks.

          The procedure used while preparing the maps of radioactive contamination is briefly described below. General procedure for mapping was the same for different contamination maps however peculiarity for each index has been taken into account. Majority of peculiarities is conditioned by ambiguity of available observation data regarding every radionuclide. Specificity of preparation of contamination maps has been considered after description of general procedures. Drafting of contamination maps consisted of successive execution of the following operations.

          Observation data acquisition and processing. Despite the fact that there are a lot of measurements of radioactive contamination values executed by different organizations the radioactive contamination fields are not completely supported by primary data. On the other hand some data sets often contradict each other. Therefore one of the main tasks during mapping was to choose the precise and representative data and to integrate data from different sources to one single array. During preliminary data processing major attention has been paid to its verification using known quantitative ratio among different radionuclides of Chornobyl discharge and its expert evaluation. Anomalous data by the results of verification have been discarded.

          Statistical direct observation data analysis. Data analysis have been executed for long-lived radionuclides of Chornobyl discharge. Statistical peculiarities of every isotope have been determined and taken into account during mapping.

          Data interpolation and plotting of the grids of contamination fields. Methods proven during mapping of the Atlas of contamination of Europe by cesium [30] have been used for data interpolation, in particular “inverse distance weights”. Application of this method ensures good results for detailed data sets. In case of data incompleteness it can result in misrepresented picture especially for anisotropic fields. For probabilistic reconstruction of contamination field along air flows of Chornobyl discharge it is necessary to execute measurements directly in the flows and on adjacent territories. In case of unavailability of these measurements the field structure cannot be precisely reconstructed. Therefore verification procedure has been applied after mapping for territories with high-gradient fields with subsequent corrections.

          During interpolation the contamination level values were calculated in square lattice nodes. This lattice is a basis for plotting of the contamination level isolines. Also lattice for separate contamination indices has been used for recalculation of contamination field levels at different dates.

          Plotting of isoline maps. The lattice of contamination field obtained during interpolation has been used while plotting the isoline maps. Restoration of isolines has been executed using the system ArcInfo (ESRI). During restoration work the generalization has been executed consisting in smoothing of lines and deleting of small outlines.

          Map verification. Utilization of formal methods for mapping does not always precisely reconstruct the structure of contamination field in particular along the "traces” and on the insufficiently investigated territories. Anomalies detected during verification have been analyzed with the purpose to determine the causes of its developments. In principle the question was whether the anomalies have been caused by inaccuracy of interpolation procedure or by the nature of input data. It should be emphasized that the majority of problematic positions have been caused by input data and more often the problems occur during integration of data from different organizations. Therefore for some territories detailed survey has been executed and after resolution of the problems with data the mapping procedure has been repeated once again. In some cases incorrect restoration of contamination field occurred due to incorrect field interpolation by inverse distance method on the grounds with significant anisotropy. Expert editing following the detailed analysis of data, additional and auxiliary information has been executed for such cases.

          Summarizing the basic principles of mapping the contamination maps are as follows:

          •application of primary observation data for mapping;


          •utilization of additional data for map verification and searching inaccuracies;


          •mapping using computer methods realized on well known commercial software;


          •expert methods for verification, generalization and editing of maps;

          •comparison of maps of contamination by different radionuclides and its mutual verification;

          •plotting of maps of contamination by different radionuclides for the same territories by the same or similar methods and algorithms.


          Specificity of plotting the contamination maps of territory by separate radionuclides is described below.

          Cesium-137. Surveys on cesium-137 have been quite complete and enable to restore the structure of contamination field by direct interpolation of observation data. The following basic sets of data are used for mapping:

          •survey of settlements of Ukraine;

          •survey of agricultural lands;

          •results of aerial gamma-spectrometry

          Other set of data has been used as auxiliary during verification and comparison of the basic data sets.

          The main problem during data preparation was during integration of the data from aerial gamma survey and gamma-spectrometrical measurement of soil samples. Examination of these data sets has shown that they reconstruct close picture of contamination field for forests however for built-over and agricultural lands some deviations may occur. Therefore aerial gamma survey results have been used only for forest lands. It should be mentioned that with the exception of some grounds there are no other reliable data of radiological survey for forests. Following the analysis and integration of data sets by cesium-137 subsequent plotting of contamination maps has been done in accordance with above mentioned scheme.

          Strontium-90. While studying the structure of radioactive contamination fields it is important to pay attention to proportion of the levels for different nuclides. Observations by strontium-90 are less complete than by cesium-137 especially for clean territories and territories with low level contamination. Therefore for determination of quantitative proportions among levels of contamination by different nuclides statistical examination of available primary observation data measured in one sample has been executed. Analysis of observation data has been executed on big amount of uniform grounds chosen on different distances from reactor along all known traces and radionuclide transport flows. Examination of available data arrays has shown that despite the correlation between the levels of Chornobyl fallouts of cesium-137 and strontium-90 the procedure of restoration of strontium-90 values on the basis of cesium-137 does not ensure the precision and confidence necessary for cartography. Generally speaking direct measurements of strontium-90 are more precise and reliable than calculations of levels of strontium-90 on the basis of levels of cesium-137. Therefore only direct observations data have been used in plotting of contamination maps by strontium-90. The following data sets have been used:

          •survey of settlements of Ukraine;


          •survey of agricultural lands.


          Additional data sets have been used for verification of final maps.

          Plotting of contamination maps has been executed by interpolation methods described earlier in this section.

          Transuranium elements. Database containing data both by sum of plutonium isotopes and by plutonium-238 has been used for plotting of maps of contamination by isotopes of plutonium and americium-241. This database contains verified measurement results executed by different organizations. In total the database contains about five thousand records. Majority of data related to contamination by americium-241 covers close zone of ChNPP and for the rest of the territory of Ukraine these data have selective nature.

          There are a lot of objective and subjective factors complicating direct application of single formalized criteria and approaches in relation to verification and plotting of contamination maps by transuranium elements:

          •both intensity of discharges and its radionuclide and disperse content have changed during the time span when contamination of territory occurred. Presence of condensate and fuel discharge components, turbulent nature of atmospheric processes of transportation and complicated nature of fallouts to Earth surface formed contamination picture with high heterogeneity.


          •in determination of contamination of a major part of the territory of Ukraine by transuranium elements it was necessary to take into account the global fallout levels that had not been thoroughly determined;


          •Geographical data have been bound basically to nearest settlement and it did not allow to account objectively existent gradients of contamination fields that significantly changed even within the same settlement.


          These factors stipulated development of methods for analysis, verification and plotting of respective contamination maps. The data from organizations that have determined a wide spectrum of long-lived radionuclides and were more reliable have been taken as a basis.

          Experimental grounds both in close zone of Chornobyl NPP and in remote regions along western and south-western traces have been used for development and justification of proposed methods. Surveys have been executed on these territories during 1988-1997 taking into account Chornobyl fallouts. As a result of these surveys the data on levels of contamination by cesium-137, strontium-90, plutonium-238, -239, -240 and americium-241 have been simultaneously collected. Analysis of proportion of cesium-137 to plutonium-239, -240 for western and south-western traces of discharge has been executed. This enabled to make conclusions on constant proportion and similarity by absolute value to fuel character of contamination along the axis of western trace and discover stable trend in relation to increasing of proportion up to the values 40 000 – 50 000 along the south-western trace confirming the condensation character of discharge on this territory. Proportion among different radionuclides has quite significant and stable trends observed in general for separate traces and contamination spots.

          So the plotting of maps of contamination of the territory of Ukraine and its separate regions by transuranium element has been executed step by step:

          •acquisition and preliminary analysis of data on transuranium element contamination;


          •analysis of additional materials (meteorological data for active discharge phase, landscape peculiarities, data on contamination by other radionuclides and respective maps etc.).


          •analysis and verification of primary observation data (geostatistical analysis, general trends of proportion among different radionuclides, verification and correction of data based on detected trends, development of predictive estimates for territories where respective data are unavailable, complementing of direct determination data by predictive data for territories highly contaminated by cesium-137 where data on transuranium elements are unavailable);


          •preparation of basic materials (modeling of proportions among radionuclides on the basis of verified data and additional field lattices, modeling of generalized lattice of cesium-137 contamination densities using all available data, plotting of the maps of transuranium element contamination densities by superposition of proportion fields and generalized lattice of cesium-137 contamination density;


          •analysis of obtained materials, expert assessment and correction taking into account the nature of forming of contamination field at different territories.


          Reference maps

          This section contains the map of stations of radiometric observation network of Hydrometeorological Service of Ukraine map of stations of radiometric observation network of Hydrometeorological Service of Ukraine by the types of observation (scale 1:5 000 000), map of soils, showing the types of soils, mechanical composition and salinization, (scale 1:5 000 000) and map of zoning of forests by density of radioactive contamination of soil by cesium-137 according to Recommendations [31] (scale 1:2 500 000) Карта: Зонування лісів за щільністю радіоактивного забруднення ґрунту цезієм-137.

          Map of soils Карта: Ґрунти is included as an illustration to show the complexity of such a phenomenon as radioactive contamination since the types of soils determine the coefficients of transition of radionuclides to plants that are the basis for human trophic chains. Part of contaminated territory is represented by meadow-mud, peat-muck and soddy-podzolic soils. Under conditions of increased humidity of the territory these types of soils facilitate to biological availability of radionuclides and its migration by trophic chains. For example transition of cesium from soil to plants on overwet meadows and in flooded places is several times higher than on upland meadows with similar soils. It is proven that major part of radiocesium in peat soil is distributed in upper layer 0-6 cm and in soddy-podzolic soils cesium migrated in vertical layer to the depth of 20 cm.

          Maps of this section have been developed by the following group of authors: O.Ye. Lytvynenko, S.V. Davydchuk, V.I. Resetnyk, V.P. Razov

          L.Ya.Tabachnyi, O.V. Gaidar, S.V. Davydchuk, O.Ye. Lytvynenko,
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>contents</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Stations of radiometric observation network of Hydrometeorological Service of Ukraine</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_75/ref_24088287_091098_75.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>Types of observations</indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Soils</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_11/ref_24088287_091098_11.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Soil group
          Soil type
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Zoning of forests by density of radioactive contamination of soil by cesium-137</leafText>
        <Description></Description>
        <link>Maps/24088287_091098_122/ref_24088287_091098_122.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>
          Limitation zone
          Limitation
          Contamination level, kBq/m2
          Contamination level, Ci/km2
        </indexedWords>
        <Frame>script</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>4</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
    </branch>

    <branch id="b05">
      <branchText>Legal and regulatory acts in the field of radiation protection (in Ukrainian)</branchText>
      <branchDescription>As of 2014 р.</branchDescription>
      <link>Norms_Laws/Index.htm</link>
      <indexedWords></indexedWords>
      <Frame>contents</Frame>
      <ImageIndex>0</ImageIndex>
      <branch id="b0501">
        <branchText>Laws of Ukraine</branchText>
        <branchDescription />
        <indexedWords></indexedWords>
        <link></link>
        <Frame>contents</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>2</ImageIndex>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Про правовий режим території, що зазнали радіоактивного забруднення внаслідок Чорнобильскої катастрофи</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Norms_laws/Laws/Law1.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Про статус і соціальний захист громадян, які постраждали внаслідок Чорнобильскої катастрофи</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Norms_laws/Laws/Law2.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Про забезпечення санітарного та епідемічного благополуччя населення</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Norms_laws/Laws/Law3.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Про використання ядерної енергії та радіаційну безпеку</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Norms_laws/Laws/Law4.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Про захист людини від впливу іонізуючих випромінювань</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Norms_laws/Laws/Law5.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Про віднесення деяких населених пунктів Волинської та Рівненської областей до зони гарантованого добровільного відселення</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Norms_laws/Laws/Law6.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Про Загальнодержавну програму подолання наслідків Чорнобильської катастрофи на 2006-2010 роки</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Norms_laws/Laws/Law7.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
      </branch>
      <branch id="b0502">
        <branchText>Regulatory acts</branchText>
        <branchDescription/>
        <link></link>
        <indexedWords></indexedWords>
        <Frame>contents</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>2</ImageIndex>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Про Концепцію проживання населення на територіях Української РСР з підвищеними рівнями радіоактивного забруднення внаслідок Чорнобильської катастрофи</leafText>
          <Description/>
          <link>Norms_laws/Norms/Norm1.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Про Положення про Національну комісію з радіаційного захисту населення України</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Norms_laws/Norms/Norm2.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Про організацію виконання постанов Верховної Ради Української РСР про порядок введення в дію законів Української РСР "Про правовий режим території, що зазнала радіоактивного забруднення внаслідок Чорнобильської катастрофи" та "Про статус і соціальний захист громадян, які постраждали внаслідок чорнобильської катастрофи"</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Norms_laws/Norms/Norm3.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Норми радіаційної безпеки України (НРБУ-97)</leafText>
          <Description/>
          <link>Norms_laws/Norms/Norm4/Nrsu_97/Title.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Норми радіаційної безпеки України (НРБУ-97/Д-2000)</leafText>
          <Description/>
          <link>Norms_laws/Norms/Norm5/Nrsu_97d_2000/Title.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Про затвердження державних санітарних правил "Основні санітарні правила забезпечення радіаційної безпеки України"</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Norms_laws/Norms/Norm6.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Про затвердження Державних гігієнічних нормативів "Допустимі рівні вмісту радіонуклідів 137Cs та 90Sr у продуктах харчування та питній воді"</leafText>
          <Description></Description>
          <link>Norms_laws/Norms/Norm7.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
      </branch>

    </branch>

    <branch id="b06">
      <branchText>Help</branchText>
      <branchDescription/>
      <link></link>
      <indexedWords></indexedWords>
      <Frame>contents</Frame>
      <ImageIndex>0</ImageIndex>
      <leaf>
        <leafText>Basic functions</leafText>
        <Description/>
        <link>help/Basic_Func_eng.htm</link>
        <indexedWords>Help Basic functions</indexedWords>
        <Frame>contents</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
      </leaf>
    </branch>
    
    <branch id="b07">
        <branchText>About Developers</branchText>
        <branchDescription/>
        <link></link>
        <indexedWords></indexedWords>
        <Frame>contents</Frame>
        <ImageIndex>2</ImageIndex>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>Ministry of Emergencies of Ukraine</leafText>
          <Description/>
          <link>Documents/about_mns_eng.htm</link>
          <indexedWords></indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
        <leaf>
          <leafText>"Intelligence Systems GEO", Ltd</leafText>
          <Description/>
          <link>Documents/about_isgeo_eng.htm</link>
          <indexedWords>"Intelligence Systems GEO, Ltd." (ISGeo) was created in 1996 by the group of experts from the V.M. Glushkov Institute of Cybernetics and is the leading Ukrainian company in the sphere of geoinformation systems (GIS) and spatial database development and implementation. ISGeo’s mission is to

give its customers best business-efficient geoinformation products, solutions and services that cover the full range of geosystems: desktop, client/server, Web- and mobile.

Highly qualified staff is hired to realize the ISGeo mission. The personnel are divided into 3 groups: information technology (IT) specialists (including programmers), GIS specialists and consultants. All they are graduates of their profile departments of the leading high education institutions, i.e. Kyiv and Moscow State Universities and Kyiv Polytechnic Institute. Two ISGeo employees have PhD degrees.

"Intelligence Systems GEO, Ltd." provides all types of geoinformation products, solutions and services including its own output software intended at creating thematic atlases, information-search cartographic systems, cartographic web-servers, geoinformation portals, register, cadastre and other systems that are based on the link of an electronic map to attribute databases.

The company develops and delivers its own information products, implemented as:
	general geographic (including topographic) electronic maps of various scales;
	electronic maps of administrative-territory division, areas, settlements;
	various thematic maps;
	administrative-territory division and population quantity electronic databases.

Other popular type of ISGeo information products is electronic atlases – such as National Atlas of Ukraine, Atlas of quantity and spatial location of population of Ukraine, Atlas of radioactive contamination of Ukraine.

During the years of its activity ISGeo has created several technological solutions that help to significantly reduce the cost of delivery and customization of these solutions to clients by reusing them.

Now the customers are being offered technologies and methodologies for:
	creating cartographic Internet servers;
	building geoinformation portals;
	creating cadastre systems;
	creating electronic atlases.

Being a long-term (since 1996) partner of the American company Pitney Bowes MapInfo Corporation (strategic partner since 2004), ISGeo delivers, implements and maintains the full range of MapInfo products in Ukraine: desktop - MapInfo Professional, VerticalMapper, Drivetime, MapX, server – SpatialWare, Web – MapXtreme, Discovery, mobile – MapX Mobile.

ISGeo also supplies software products of other producers: Avenza Inc. (Canada), Infotech Europe (Great Britain), PCI Geomatics Inc. (Canada), SpacEyes (France).

Our clients are such well known companies and organizations as Beeline, DCC/Astelit, UMC (MTS), Ukrtelecom, Raiffeisen Bank Aval, Index-bank, Nadra, UkrPromBank, UkrSocBank, SkyLock Ukraine, Benish GPS Ukraine, KE KievPassTrans, Tumen Oil Company Ukraine, Coca Cola Beverages Ukraine, Slavutich, Philip Morris Ukraine, Procter Gamble Ukraine, Avon Cosmetics Ukraine, AC Nielsen Ukraine, Ministry of Emergency Measures of Ukraine, Visicom, Cartography enterprise, "KievGeoInformatica" enterprise, SwedeSurvey (Sweden), GRS (Germany), IRSN (France), etc.
Intelligence Systems GEO Ltd
02094, Kyiv, Popudrenka St. 54 office 1
Tel/fax: +380-(44)-338-01-82
Інтернет: www.isgeo.kiev.ua
E-mail: company@isgeo.kiev.ua
Web-site www.isgeo.com.ua </indexedWords>
          <Frame>contents</Frame>
          <ImageIndex>5</ImageIndex>
        </leaf>
      </branch>
  </Tree>
</Root>